Register of the Aristide Rieffel Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Aristide Rieffel papers,
1888-1941
76065
Rieffel, Aristide, 1859-1941
46 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (19.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, pamphlets, clippings, and photographs, relating primarily to the temperance movement in France and the United States, pacifism, international arbitration, the Society for Arbitration between Nations, Alfred Nobel and the Nobel Peace Prize.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1976.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1859 Born as Arthur Zacharin Rieffel in Paris, France
1890s Participates in the international pacifist movement as a member of the Société française pour l'arbitrage entre nations
ca. 1915 Emigrates to the United States, living first in New York and then in Santa Barbara
1941 Died
Scope and Content Note
The Aristide Rieffel papers in the Hoover Institution Archives consist primarily of published and unpublished notes and writings, including a significant number of articles written for French language newspapers in the United States, the country in which Rieffel spent the latter part of his life. Most of these writings pertain to Rieffel's vision of a moral crusade to reform modern society, which he saw as being prone to violence and corrupted by pervasive alcoholism. The abolition of warfare and the prohibition of alcohol consumption were the causes to which Rieffel devoted most of his life.
While never a strict pacifist, Rieffel associated himself with efforts to eliminate warfare through diplomacy and arbitration, and this activity drew him into contact with Alfred Nobel, Frédéric Passy, Charles Richet, Bertha von Suttner, and other peace advocates in Europe. For Rieffel, the attainment of world peace was predicated on a change in educational practices in order to eliminate what he perceived to be the "bellicose instinct" in humanity. This, in turn, was linked by Rieffel to the goal of eradicating alcoholism, which he saw as being at the root of virtually all societal problems.
In many respects, Rieffel was at odds with the idea of mass democracy. Instead, he favored the rule of an educated elite of "savants," in whose number Rieffel clearly included himself. Throughout his writing career, Rieffel argued in favor of what he called the "vote familial," or family vote, an electoral system in which votes would be weighted according to family size, with parents voting on behalf of their children. According to Rieffel, such a system would provide a "moderating" influence on society, which otherwise tended toward extremism.
In addition to numerous writings on politics, society, and religion, the collection contains examples of Rieffel's correspondence with Nobel, Passy, and von Suttner, as well as with prominent figures in the temperance movements in the United States and France, including Maurice Legrain and Mary Frances Stoddard.
The Aristide Rieffel collection in the Hoover Institution Archives was acquired in 1976, with increments added in 1978 and 1983. The remainder of Rieffel's papers can be found in the holdings of the University of California at Santa Barbara, and an inventory for the Santa Barbara collection can be consulted in the Hoover Institution Archives.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Society for Arbitration between Nations.; Arbitration, International.; Nobel prizes.; Pacifism.; Peace.; Temperance.; France.; United States.; Nobel, Alfred Bernhard, 1833-1896.
Occupations
Journalists.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1892-1978. (Box 1)
  Bibliographies, brochures, and clippings, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1892-1940. (Box 1-3)
  Letters and enclosures, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1888-1941. (Box 3-45)
  Articles, notes, and letters to the editor, arranged chronologically by title. Includes related correspondence
- Subject File, 1888-1938. (Box 46)
  Clippings, membership list, resolutions, serial issues, and pamphlets, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Photographs, 1892-1929. (Box 46)
  Eight prints and seven negatives depicting Aristide Rieffel, Hodgson Pratt, William T. Stead, Colonel Picquart, Frédéric Passy, Ernesto Teodora Moneta, Berthe von Suttner, and Louis Forest
- Oversize Material, 1921. (Box 47)
  One poster, with a color illustration, advertising the French antialcohol newspaper, Fraternité
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1892-1978 (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies, 1928-1978. (Folder 1: 1)
    Consists primarily of annotated lists of Rieffel's publications, with commentary by his daughter, Mirielle
  - Brochures, ca. 1920. (Folder 1: 2)
    Materials relating to the Ecole Française de New York and the French School for Girls, Rome, both of which were directed by Rieffel's wife, Jeanne
  - Clippings, 1892-1936 (Folder 1: 3)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1892-1940
  - Unidentified (Folder 1: 4)
  - Anti-Saloon League of New York, 1919-1922 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Atlantic Monthly, 1916 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Barrès, Maurice, n.d. (Folder 1: 7)
  - Bellamy, Henri, 1923 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Bertrand, Pierre, 1925 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Bonnet, C., 1936 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Buisson, Ferdinand, 1919-1925 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1918 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Carrel, Alexis, n.d. (Folder 1: 13)
  - Cauvin, Gustave, 1921-1922 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Colby, F. M., 1923 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Coolidge, Calvin, n.d. (Folder 1: 16)
  - Couchoud, L., 1924 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Courrier des États-Unis, 1921-1923 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Droucy, R., 1921 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Dumay, Henri, 1919-1923 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Farchy, Charles, 1931 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Fontaine, H. La, 1917 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Forest, Louis, 1921 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Gandacheau, A., n.d. (Folder 1: 24)
  - Ganzert, Frederic W., 1935 (Folder 1: 25)
  - Guego, F., 1917 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Guernut, (?), n.d. (Folder 2: 2)
  - Hayes, Alfred, 1919 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Haynes, (?), n.d. (Folder 2: 4)
  - Hericourt, Jules, 1918-1931 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Herriot, Edouard, n.d. (Folder 2: 6)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1931 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Jèze, Gaston, 1925 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Legrain, Maurice, 1921-1924 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Librairies E. Flammarion et A. Vaillant, 1923 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Libby, Frederick J., 1935 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Loeb, Jacques, 1916-1919 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Loeb, Leonard, n.d. (Folder 2: 13)
  - Millikan, Robert, 1893 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Moch, Gaston, 1923 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Moneta, Ernesto Teodoro, 1893 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Nobel, Alfred, 1892-1896 (Folder 2: 17)
  - Passy, Frédéric, 1894-1895. (Folder 2: 18)
    Includes one letter addressed to Passy by A. Puigho
  - Peabody, Frederick W., 1926 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Le Progrès civique, 1923 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Puaux, René, 1920 (Folder 2: 21)
  - Richet, Charles, 1913-1932 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Santa Barbara News-Press, 1939 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Sardoy, Paul, n.d. (Folder 3: 3)
  - Stoddard, Cora Frances, 1920-1926 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Stojowsky, (?), n.d. (Folder 3: 5)
  - Streit, Clarence, 1940 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Suttner, Bertha von, 1892 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Le Temps, n.d. (Folder 3: 8)
  - Trolle, P., 1933 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Vaury, Georges, 1916 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Ware, (?), n.d. (Folder 3: 11)
  - Wood, W., 1928 (Folder 3: 12)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1888-1941
  - General.
    Undated notebooks containing holograph drafts of letters and other writings
    - General. (Folder 3: 13)
      Two notebooks containing writings on France and Germany
    - One notebook labelled "Impérialisme et socialisme sont même chose," "L'intelligence ne compte pas" (Folder 3: 14)
    - One notebook labelled "L'intelligence ne compte pas," "La fin d'un beau rêve: l'amitié franco-allemande" (Folder 3: 15)
    - One notebook labelled "Lettre à Blumenthal," "Destruction de la patrie américaine par les Américains," "Affaire Dreyfus, question juive" (Folder 3: 16)
    - One notebook labelled "Lettre à Buisson," "La natation" (Folder 3: 17)
    - One notebook labelled "Lettre à Stoddard dénonçant l'école," "Comment on entretient l'antijudaisme," "Destruction de la patrie américaine par les Américains" (Folder 3: 18)
    - One notebook labelled "Sion," "Napoléon" (Folder 3: 19)
  - "Le 11 novembre, jour de deuil national," n.d. (Box-folder 4: 1)
    Holograph
  - "Le 11 novembre, la moralité humaine a fait faillite," n.d. (Folder 4: 2)
  - "17 propositions," n.d. (Folder 4: 3)
  - "L'adultère cause de dépopulation," n.d. (Folder 4: 4)
  - "L'alcool," n.d. (Folder 4: 5)
  - "L'alcool et la noyade," n.d. (Folder 4: 6)
  - "Alcool et vices," n.d. (Folder 4: 7)
  - "L'alcool, question internationale," n.d. (Folder 4: 8)
    Holograph fragment and notes
  - "Alcool, un acte de trahison," n.d. (Folder 4: 9)
    Holograph and clippings
  - "L'alcoolisme," n.d. (Folder 4: 10)
    Holograph notes
  - "L'alcoolisme en France," n.d. (Folder 4: 11)
  - "L'alcoolsime et le sentiment de la dignité," n.d. (Folder 4: 12)
  - "L'Allemagne attaquera," n.d. (Folder 4: 13)
  - "Les Allemands sont-ils civilisés?" n.d. (Folder 4: 14)
  - "Alliance avec l'Islam pour la prohibition," n.d. (Folder 4: 15)
  - "L'alliance du Vatican et du bistro," n.d. (Folder 4: 16)
  - "Américains, sauvez la France condamnée à périr d'alcoolisme," n.d. (Folder 4: 17)
  - "L'Amérique à Genève serait-elle une alliée de la France?" n.d. (Folder 4: 18)
  - "Amérique, déchristianisation," n.d. (Folder 4: 19)
  - "L'amour de l'humanité et l'amour de la patrie, sont-ils en antagonisme?" n.d. (Folder 4: 20)
  - "L'annexation de l'Alsace – cause de la guerre actuelle," n.d. (Folder 4: 21)
  - "L'antagonisme de l'instinct grégaire et de l'instinct maternel," n.d. (Folder 4: 22)
  - "L'anticléricalisme n'est qu'une aggravation des vices de l'Eglise Romaine," n.d. (Folder 4: 23)
  - "Les anticléricaux, le féminisme," n.d. (Folder 4: 24)
  - "L'Anti-Saloon League et la politique," n.d. (Folder 4: 25)
  - "L'arbitrage est un leurre," n.d. (Folder 4: 26)
  - Article on France, n.d. (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Article on taxes for La Revue scientifique, n.d. (Folder 5: 2)
  - "L'attitude des socialistes dans la question du latin," n.d. (Folder 5: 3)
  - "Attitude scientifique, attitude pragmatique," n.d. (Folder 5: 4)
  - "L'autorité du pape a été fortifiée par les anticléricaux français," n.d. (Folder 5: 5)
  - "Aux Alsaciens," n.d. (Folder 5: 6)
  - "Avertissement aux Américains," n.d. (Folder 5: 7)
  - "L'avilissement des personnes politiques," n.d. (Folder 5: 8)
  - "Les avilissements," n.d. (Folder 5: 9)
  - "Ayez pitié de vos enfants," n.d. (Folder 5: 10)
  - "Boches et Yiddish," n.d. (Folder 5: 11)
  - "Le bouddhisme des Français," n.d. (Folder 5: 12)
  - "La boxe," n.d. (Folder 5: 13)
  - "La brimade du 4 décembre," n.d. (Folder 5: 14)
  - "Butler," n.d. (Folder 5: 15)
  - "Le buveur est un criminel à cause du mal que fait l'alcool," n.d. (Folder 5: 16)
  - "California," n.d. (Folder 5: 17)
  - "Capitalisme = Socialisme," n.d. (Folder 5: 18)
  - "Le caractère des Français," n.d. (Folder 5: 19)
  - "Les caractéristiques de la France, de l'Angleterre, de l'Allemagne," n.d. (Folder 5: 20)
  - "Carpentier, boxeur," n.d. (Folder 5: 21)
  - "Le catholicisme, la théorie de l'évolution, et la morale," n.d. (Folder 5: 22)
  - "La cause de la dépopulation," n.d. (Folder 5: 23)
  - "La cause de l'hyphénisme," n.d. (Folder 5: 24)
  - "La cause du désastre italien: la solidarité du Vatican et de l'Autriche," n.d. (Folder 5: 25)
  - "Causes de l'alcoolisme en France," n.d. (Folder 5: 26)
  - "Causes de la misère," n.d. (Folder 5: 27)
  - "Causes de la prospérité et de la décadence des États-Unis," n.d. (Folder 6: 1)
  - "Causes du gaspillage," n.d. (Folder 6: 2)
  - "Ce n'est pas l'agresseur qui refuse l'arbitrage," n.d. (Folder 6: 3)
  - "Ce qu'est la Révolution," n.d. (Folder 6: 4)
  - "Ce qu'est l'équité," n.d. (Folder 6: 5)
  - "Ce qu'il faut savoir pour avoir le droit de faire de la politique," n.d. (Folder 6: 6)
  - "Ce que doivent être les législateurs," n.d. (Folder 6: 7)
  - "Cessez de confondre le droit, la justice et l'équité," n.d. (Folder 6: 8)
  - "Changement de constitution," n.d. (Folder 6: 9)
  - "Le chantage des débitants des boissons," n.d. (Folder 6: 10)
  - "La chasteté des musulmanes," n.d. (Folder 6: 11)
  - "Chat noir, les arabes," n.d. (Folder 6: 12)
  - "Christianisme et natalité," n.d. (Folder 6: 13)
  - "La civilisation ne s'apprend pas," n.d. (Folder 6: 14)
  - "Civisme," n.d. (Folder 6: 15)
  - "Le code de l'humanité," n.d. (Folder 6: 16)
  - "Combativité," n.d. (Folder 6: 17)
  - "Comment abolir la guerre?" n.d. (Folder 6: 18)
  - "Comment enseigner la natation," n.d. (Folder 6: 19)
  - "Comment il faut ne pas élever nos filles," n.d. (Folder 6: 20)
  - "Comment instaurer la paix," n.d. (Folder 6: 22)
  - "Comment l'Allemagne peut payer," n.d. (Folder 6: 23)
  - "Comment l'éducation doit être réglée pour réaliser un monde pacifique donc prospère," n.d. (Folder 6: 24)
  - "Comment la France est tombée dans une trappe," n.d. (Folder 6: 25)
  - "Comment les antipatriotes acquièrent le titre des patriotes," n.d. (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - "Comment obtenir que les élèves voient dans leur maître un ami?" n.d. (Folder 7: 2)
  - "Comment réformer l'éducation américaine des filles," n.d. (Folder 7: 3)
  - "Conférence internationale de pacification par l'éducation," n.d. (Folder 7: 4)
  - "Conflit du patriotisme et du Catholicisme en France depuis 1848," n.d. (Folder 7: 5)
  - "Congrès d'anthropologie et d'ethnographie," n.d. (Folder 7: 6)
  - "La conquête de la Syrie," n.d. (Folder 7: 7)
  - "La conscription," n.d. (Folder 7: 8)
  - "Conséquences pour l'Église du triomphe de la république," n.d. (Folder 7: 9)
  - "La constitution," n.d. (Folder 7: 10)
  - "La contribution de la France au progrès," n.d. (Folder 7: 11)
  - "Conventions internationales," n.d. (Folder 7: 12)
  - "La conversion des Allemands," n.d. (Folder 7: 13)
  - "Les corollaires," n.d. (Folder 7: 14)
  - "Corruption du monde par l'Allemagne," n.d. (Folder 7: 15)
  - "Croyance et pratique aujourd'hui," n.d. (Folder 7: 16)
  - "Le culte du drapeau," n.d. (Folder 7: 17)
  - "Le culte du mensonge," n.d. (Folder 7: 18)
  - "Dans la Société des Nations, les États-Unis seraient-ils un facteur de pacification mondiale?" n.d. (Folder 7: 19)
  - "De la propriété intellectuelle," n.d. (Folder 7: 20)
  - "La décadence," n.d. (Folder 7: 21)
  - "Déclaration des droits de l'homme," n.d. (Folder 7: 22)
  - "Déclaration des droits des nations," n.d. (Folder 7: 23)
  - "Déclaration pour le salut de la France," n.d. (Folder 7: 24)
  - "La défense nationale compromise par la littérature," n.d. (Folder 7: 25)
  - "La défense nationale empêchée par le latin," n.d. (Folder 7: 26)
  - "La définition de l'imbécile," n.d. (Folder 7: 27)
  - "Définition de l'Islam," n.d. (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - "Définition de la civilisation, origine de l'équité," n.d. (Folder 8: 2)
  - "Délivrez la France de la bistrocratie," n.d. (Folder 8: 3)
  - "La démocratisation de la France," n.d. (Folder 8: 4)
  - "La destruction de la France par ses politiciens," n.d. (Folder 8: 5)
  - "Destruction de la patrie américaine par les Américains," n.d. (Folder 8: 6)
  - "La destruction du peuple français par le régime de la 3ème république," n.d. (Folder 8: 7)
  - "Les deux conceptions de l'alcool," n.d. (Folder 8: 8)
  - "Les deux morales," n.d. (Folder 8: 9)
  - "Deux parties," n.d. (Folder 8: 10)
  - "Les deux principes," n.d. (Folder 8: 11)
  - "Les deux principes de la conduite humaine," n.d. (Folder 8: 12)
  - "Les deux principes sociaux," n.d. (Folder 8: 13)
  - "Les deux religions," n.d. (Folder 8: 14)
  - "Le devoir du savant," n.d. (Folder 8: 15)
  - "Différence entre l'intelligence et l'instinct," n.d. (Folder 8: 16)
  - "La digestion, la manducation," n.d. (Folder 8: 17)
  - "Dignité," n.d. (Folder 8: 18)
  - "La diminution de l'intelligence par les études classiques," n.d. (Folder 8: 19)
  - "La doctrine de l'espoir," n.d. (Folder 8: 20)
  - "La doctrine du vote familial," n.d. (Folder 8: 21)
  - "Les données du problème (Société des Nations)," n.d. (Folder 8: 22)
  - "La douche dans les écoles," n.d. (Folder 8: 23)
  - "Droit de grève," n.d. (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - "Le droit de l'homme," n.d. (Folder 9: 2)
    Holograph and printed matter
  - "Les droits de l'homme," n.d. (Folder 9: 3)
  - "L'École," n.d. (Folder 9: 4)
  - "École américaine, facteur de l'alcoolisme," n.d. (Folder 9: 5)
  - "Éducation," n.d. (Folder 9: 6)
  - "L'éducation américaine," n.d. (Folder 9: 7)
  - "L'éducation américaine des filles est antisociale," n.d. (Folder 9: 8)
  - "Éducation américaine, éducation des Jésuites," n.d. (Folder 9: 9)
  - "Éducation en Amérique," n.d. (Folder 9: 10)
  - "Effets du militarisme en temps de paix," n.d. (Folder 9: 11)
  - "Égalitarisme, facteur de mort pour la France," n.d. (Folder 9: 12)
  - "L'Église," n.d. (Folder 9: 13)
  - "L'Église et l'équité," n.d. (Folder 9: 14)
    Holograph notes and clippings
  - "Einstein," n.d. (Folder 9: 15)
  - "Einstein et Clémence Royer," n.d. (Folder 9: 16)
  - "Einstein le malfaiteur," n.d. (Folder 9: 17)
  - "Les éléments constitutifs de la pudeur," n.d. (Folder 9: 18)
  - "Ellis Island," n.d. (Folder 9: 19)
  - "Ellis Island et la Ligue des Droits de l'Homme," n.d. (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - "L'émigration aux États-Unis," n.d. (Folder 10: 2)
  - "En quoi consiste la paix," n.d. (Folder 10: 3)
  - "En quoi je suis utile," n.d. (Folder 10: 4)
  - "En quoi le service militaire obligatoire en Amérique peut être nuisible aux Alliés," n.d. (Folder 10: 5)
  - "L'enseignement classique empêche de concevoir la réalité," n.d. (Folder 10: 6)
  - "Équité, civilisation," n.d. (Folder 10: 7)
  - "L'équité est le principe unique," n.d. (Folder 10: 8)
  - "L'équité par l'isolement," n.d. (Folder 10: 9)
  - "L'ère nouvelle," n.d. (Folder 10: 10)
  - "L'erreur à Washington des pauvres Français," n.d. (Folder 10: 11)
  - "Les erreurs fondamentales de notre démocratie," n.d. (Folder 10: 12)
  - "L'esclavage des Français par les effets de l'alcool," n.d. (Folder 10: 13)
  - "L'esprit de soumission," n.d. (Folder 10: 14)
  - "L'essence du Christianisme," n.d. (Folder 10: 15)
  - "Les États-Unis dans la Société des Nations seraient-ils un facteur de paix?" n.d. (Folder 10: 16)
  - "Les études classiques empêchent l'homme d'être honnête," n.d. (Folder 10: 17)
  - "Évangile selon Jean," n.d. (Folder 10: 18)
  - "L'évolution des religions," n.d. (Folder 10: 19)
  - "Exaltation des crapules," n.d. (Folder 10: 20)
  - "Facteurs historiques de la moralité," n.d. (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - "Faillite de l'anticléricalisme," n.d. (Folder 11: 2)
  - "Faillite de la foi," n.d. (Folder 11: 3)
  - "La faillite de la laïcisation," n.d. (Folder 11: 4)
  - "La familiarité," n.d. (Folder 11: 5)
  - "Faut-il, pour le salut de l'humanité, continuer cette guerre?" n.d. (Folder 11: 6)
  - "Faut-il détruire la méchanceté?" n.d. (Folder 11: 7)
  - "Le féminisme," n.d. (Folder 11: 8)
  - "Le féminisme est une régression," n.d. (Folder 11: 9)
  - "La fin du beau rêve," n.d. (Folder 11: 10)
  - "Fondation d'un institut d'aptitude au mariage," n.d. (Folder 11: 11)
  - "Fondement de la morale," n.d. (Folder 11: 12-14)
  - "Fondement de ma morale," n.d. (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - "Les formes de réalisation de l'instinct sexuel," n.d. (Folder 12: 2)
  - "Fragilité de l'homme," n.d. (Folder 12: 3)
  - "La fragilité des êtres supérieurs," n.d. (Folder 12: 4)
  - "Les Français ne boivent pas assez d'eau," n.d. (Folder 12: 5)
  - "Les Français ont fêté Napoléon. Pourquoi?" n.d. (Folder 12: 6)
  - "France = principe de liberté, Allemagne = principe d'autorité," n.d. (Folder 12: 7)
  - "La France ruinée par la littérature classique," n.d. (Folder 12: 8)
  - "La France victime des historiens," n.d. (Folder 12: 9)
  - "La future loi d'immigration," n.d. (Folder 12: 10)
  - "Gardienne de la vie de la nation," n.d. (Folder 12: 11)
  - "Genèse de la morale," n.d. (Folder 12: 12)
  - "La géographie et les traités de Washington," n.d. (Folder 12: 13)
  - "La gloire de l'Islam," n.d. (Folder 12: 14)
  - "La grande merveille de cette guerre," n.d. (Folder 12: 15)
  - "La gravitation est-elle une force?" n.d. (Folder 12: 16)
  - "La guerre entretenue par les sports," n.d. (Folder 12: 17)
  - "La guerre est-elle l'oeuvre des capitalistes?" n.d. (Folder 12: 18)
  - "La guerre par le désarmement," n.d. (Folder 12: 19)
  - "La guerre sans militarisme," n.d. (Folder 12: 20)
  - "La hiérarchie des droits," n.d. (Folder 12: 21)
  - "L'homme et ses sentiments," n.d. (Folder 12: 22)
  - "Idées principales," n.d. (Box-folder 13: 1)
  - "Il faut que tout le monde vive," n.d. (Folder 13: 2)
  - "Il n'y a pas de partis, il y a seulement les pacifiques et les violents," n.d. (Folder 13: 3)
  - "Il n'y a pas de place sur cette planète pour tout le monde," n.d. (Folder 13: 4)
  - "Il n'y a pas de race germanique," n.d. (Folder 13: 5)
  - "Immoralité et dangers du Sionisme," n.d. (Folder 13: 6)
  - "Impérialisme," n.d. (Folder 13: 7)
  - "L'impérialisme juif contre la France," n.d. (Folder 13: 8)
  - "L'impérialisme nordique," n.d. (Folder 13: 9)
  - "L'impérialisme yankee," n.d. (Folder 13: 10)
  - "L'impôt = vol," n.d. (Folder 13: 11)
  - "L'impôt est un vol," n.d. (Folder 13: 12)
  - "L'inconscience dans l'éducation," n.d. (Folder 13: 13)
  - "L'inefficacité de la Société des Nations," n.d. (Folder 13: 14)
  - "L'inévitable conquête de la France par les alliés," n.d. (Folder 13: 15)
  - "L'instinct, les émotions," n.d. (Folder 13: 16)
  - "Instinct grégaire," n.d. (Folder 13: 17)
  - "L'intelligence ne compte pas," n.d. (Folder 13: 18)
  - "Les juifs exclus de l'immigration américaine," n.d. (Folder 13: 19)
  - "Justice aux socialistes," n.d. (Folder 13: 20)
  - "Justice collective," n.d. (Folder 13: 21)
  - "Le Kaiser au bagne," n.d. (Folder 13: 22)
  - "Latin," n.d. (Box-folder 14: 1)
  - "Le latin, facteur de l'impérialisme," n.d. (Folder 14: 2)
  - "La leçon du nègre," n.d. (Folder 14: 3)
  - "Léon XIII," n.d. (Folder 14: 4)
  - "La Ligue des Droits de l'Homme," n.d. (Folder 14: 5)
    Holograph and clipping
  - "Liste des propositions," n.d. (Folder 14: 6)
  - "La loi Falloux," n.d. (Folder 14: 7)
  - "La loi Johnson," n.d. (Folder 14: 8)
  - "La loi Volstead," n.d. (Folder 14: 9)
  - "La lutte, facteur du triomphe en politique," n.d. (Folder 14: 10)
  - "La lutte pour les priviligiés," n.d. (Folder 14: 11)
  - "M. Hughes travaille pour la guerre," n.d. (Folder 14: 12)
  - "Mais les chefs sont élus," n.d. (Folder 14: 13)
  - "Le mal est en vous," n.d. (Folder 14: 14)
  - "Le mal fait par l'alcool," n.d. (Folder 14: 15)
  - "Le mariage du Kaiser et la doctrine du pardon," n.d. (Folder 14: 16)
  - "La méchanceté humaine," n.d. (Folder 14: 17)
  - "La mission de la Ligue des Droits de l'Homme," n.d. (Folder 14: 18)
  - "Moeurs américaines," n.d. (Folder 14: 19)